I love and welcome to Laurie game 2019
to be honest I was planning to do a kind
of a speech but then I started doing
other stuff and then it became Sunday
and Monday and Tuesday and here we are
but I did actually I did I did a start
and I wanted to do it right now okay so
um welcome to another game 2019 my name
is Jacob Riis I'm the program director
and this is the 16th edition of the
conference yeah right
[Applause]
sweet 16 that is the year when an
annoying child becomes an even more
annoying child so I'm quite happy nor
the game it's a conference and not a
child not least because I would then
have three kids now with three different
moms and one of the moms would be called
Eric Robertson okay that was a swag
I had got in my speech okay but actually
there's a little bit of truth to the
analogy here because I don't know how
many of you have been to not a game
before whoa nice to see you again
and you've noticed that the child that
we call nor the game have has changed a
little bit for this year right you know
there's a new entrance have you noticed
that yeah obviously and and I know it's
kind of confusing but also because we've
chosen to call the auditorium's the same
names but then turn them around and
shift it just to make it even more
confusing also so that you actually use
this print program that we have spent
hours on producing right so I just want
to highlight a bit of what is in store
for the next three days we have 140
speakers ready for you I think from my
perspective this is one of the strongest
programs I've ever been part of
producing there's a lot of great content
in there and it will start as soon as
I'm done because I'm not part of that
but I will really really say that you
should go to as many lectures as you can
besides doing all the other stuff and
all the other stuff is of course
business I know a lot of us are here to
do business actually not you because
then you would be at the meet to match
already and you wouldn't be sitting here
right but I know they have already
broken all records it's something like I
don't know 3000
something meetings that are going to be
held to during these three days and it's
it's incredible
so that part is also really good the
publisher market is going on right now
where developers meeting publishers and
one thing that is another kind of
bastard child that I have made is the
Nordic game discovery contest I don't
know if you've noticed but we have 17
games and display in the expo area from
all parts of the world even from South
Africa they have all been through
qualification rounds of our pitching
competition and now they're here and
their games are on display and the thing
that are their tasks for the next two
days is to convince you to vote for them
so that four of the best of them goes on
to the final on Friday where they will
battle here on stage which I will also
urge you to come and see because it's
highly entertaining seeing people
getting roasted and I am the host and it
would be so much fun
and also the judges among the judges
will be Warren Spector he will be
sitting there and roast people and I
don't know I'm gonna be there I hope you
will too then another new thing is I
mean we always do a lot of social events
and we always did our gala dinner this
year we've tried something completely
new and I'm really looking forward to it
we call it the Nordic game dinner
experience because it's not a gala
dinner anymore and it's not a sit-down
where you get forced to sit and talk to
annoying people all night you can
actually walk around and it's not taking
place here either so we have buses
driving you to the venue called morsken
but all the info obviously is here or in
our website so you can read more about
it I hope that you have registered for
the dinner if if not it's too late I
guess but then you can always join the
party afterwards which will be at the
same venue there so please do that
because there I have the most insane
project going on with a metal band with
musicians from all over the world
playing to a game that will be played
live by an influencer and streamed while
the band is playing music live and us
audience can be there to cheer I don't
know I've never seen anything like that
so I hope that it will be a success and
not crash so and then everything
culminates obviously on Friday with the
discovery day where we have even more
games on display we end up here with the
contest finals and after that the wrap
up with you know a lot of ceremonial
stuff where you can win tickets for next
year and I think that we will announce
the dates for next year even so please
please please if you have the health and
the endurance
please stay all through the next three
days until Friday at I think eight
o'clock in the evening where we finally
lie down and die and then I'm actually
done I think I welcome you all thank you
so much for coming
I'm not gonna say thank you to all these
people that are helping me and Eric by
making this conference yet we will do
that on Friday after we've seen how they
performed but the only thing I have left
to say is now you're in for a treat the
opening keynote is from a very very
talented woman
Anastasia Oh Parra I was almost saying
opera not no not the browser not the
browser from new Swedish studio embark I
don't know if you've heard about them
but I have and I expect great things
from them so with no further ado please
welcome Anna Sasha please come up on
stage thank you so much and see you
around
[Music]
okay hi okay let's start so I don't know
about you but I like spending time on
making the first slide of my
presentation I end up tweaking it
endlessly and so it's just right but
finding the style I'd like to commit to
Matt next time and usually I find myself
exploring less creative options than I
would like to so I decided that this
time I'll make a few but very different
so start with this one okay I was like
hundred percent sold but I like the
sketchiness of it so I tried another one
actually maybe with more fuzzy letters
yeah like this or maybe was more colored
or more like Van Gogh starry night or
maybe an actual starry night but it kind
of looks sleepy maybe more powerful with
fire and aggression or the country a
chilled winter forest but yeah as you
probably have guessed by now each image
is generated and image each image you
see took only 20 seconds to make with
texture synthesis and a mixing from a
single example so I'm an assayer parent
and I'm a procedural artist Adam Park
studios and I'm very excited to be
presenting for you today so in total I
generated about 3,000 interest lights by
having a library of roughly 150 images
as examples and I also made six guides
which were to dictate composition and
contrast and then I just let the picture
synthesis fun while I was doing
something else and then I came back and
just cherry picked what I liked and this
ability to explore so many ideas and
combinations quickly and the thrill of
finding combinations that would work and
just seeing what happens in where he can
take me creatively that was a lot of fun
it was like a visual brainstorm on
steroids and the main principle of the
algorithm is not very complicated every
pixel simply asks if it's um my neighbor
what is my color and the answer to the
question is the example in which we
provide so the example image itself is a
program that every pixel follows but hey
does it mean we're programming by giving
an example and the answer is yes and I
think it is why example based synthesis
is so interesting oh yeah you can make
pretty trippy gifs every generating a
couple of variations at embark we
believe that it should be as easy to
create as it is to play which requires
us to rethink the way we create today
and I believe one way to approach the
vision of accessible creation is by
enabling to effortlessly sculpt and
navigate creative possibility space so
what do I even mean with sculpting
possibility space tools define our
workflows that is why one of my main
fascinations with procedural ism comes
from the power to define what I
artistically want via a set of rules
so I basically encode my own artistic
process and decision making into an
algorithm and that algorithm in turn
outputs a space of generated outcomes
that are following the rules I described
and I can sculpt the space by
manipulating algorithm and as a
mechanism for navigation through the
space I can add sliders or other
parameters that are treated as inputs to
my carefully designed functions but
making tools requires a lot of knowledge
that is often orthogonal to content
creator skills and it also requires to
disrupt the creative flow and step in to
translate what you wants as a program
understands mindset and it is also time
consuming but imagine if we could define
a space of possibilities by providing
examples of what you want and have a
program extract relevant rules from this
examples then we can immediately jump
into the exploration of the generative
space without needing to manually craft
the points for exploring or the
algorithm itself thus always staying
within the creative iteration loop and
in the end we will probably converge in
a point where satisfied with
and this point in this Malibu by example
space can be reused as an example for
the next space week or maybe someone
else designs and because of the example
based nature these spaces have a format
intuitive to both read and write
meaning that content creators will be
able to create their own tools by doing
what they already do best making awesome
stuff and of course getting that
workflow is a long journey and even
though we have many ideas on how to get
there we don't have all the answers and
it's most likely not the answer but a
piece of an overall puzzle and we are at
the very beginning of our exploration
where picture synthesis the topic of
this talk is just a small step towards a
bigger vision
well ultimately we are interested in
creation of full 3d interactive
experiences ok so now that we have a bit
of whys let's talk about technical house
so how does texture synthesis work and
also a brief and totally incomplete
history of non parametric texture
synthesis so when working with
procedural systems I often design a
top-down hierarchical approach where I
determine a strict sequence of generator
chains which operate in a dependency
isolation from one another so let's say
we want to make a procedural house then
we would start with generating sealer
and that sealer Duty should commands for
other generators to be placed
but before passing it to doors windows
and other modules it would determine
locations and handle dependencies so the
next generators will receive information
that is unaffected by other generators
outcomes so when making the doorknobs
and wooden planks we can be quite sure
that would not suddenly miss up the
chimney and that allows us to break down
a complex task into small and manageable
chunks which is amazing if we are only
interested in top-down questions such as
if this is my psyllid where are the
windows however if we ask a reverse
question if the windows are here what is
the house the generator will not be able
to answer but what would happen if
instead of having a hierarchy of
commands we would have a self-organizing
system of simple elements where each
contributes to a collective emergent
and to make this explanation a bit more
approachable I present you your hosts
today
meet the color blobs of pixel down
they're extremely social beings who love
to hang out with other color blobs by
coordinating zai colours together and
they are looking for a new home and so
happens that we are about to synthesize
a whole bunch of new pixels for a new
image so let's imagine that the image we
want to make or to generate is in fact a
perfectly grid like pixel down where
every pixel cell is a house waiting for
a color blob occupant however we have a
specific visual goal in mind you want to
generate something that looks like an
example image so how do we communicate
that to the color blobs when they start
moving in well we provide them with an
example image itself but deconstruct it
into neighborhood patterns and the
corresponding pixel color that should be
placed if a specific pattern is
encountered so you can think of it as an
instruction manual that tells each color
blob what colors they should be if the
neighbors are in particular color
combination
so in this examples if my colors are
light green I would also be like green
and if my colors a dark green I also
become dark green and we have a lot of
this kind of rules basically as many as
we can break the image into and here is
just a visualization of deconstructing
an image into 3 by 3 neighborhood
patterns and as you can see this image
is just 50 by 50 but you know you know
in a bit we will end up actually was
quite a few patterns in our menu and you
can imagine if the picture is bigger we
get much more patterns and this is just
three by three patterns so how did
pixels or color blobs even use all these
patterns
so let's investigate a good example so
here's Bob Hope's the color block and he
plans to move into the pixel town but
before he can do that he needs to know
what color complements bests to his
existing neighbors so he goes around his
neighbors and records everyone he saw
and in what order and if no one moved in
he also checks that so what Bob does is
a construction of his neighborhood
color pattern
then Bob checks the menu and he goes
through the list of all possible
patterns and let's remove the neighbors
that are not present we can compare
easier and as you can see it might so
happen that there is no exact match but
that doesn't stop Bob as he decides oh
well I will try to follow the manual as
best as I can so Bob chooses the closest
matching color pattern there's a pattern
of his neighbors and sure as the purple
is a little bit off it's more like brown
here
but hey otherwise it's a pretty good
guess so Bob takes the color associated
with that pattern as his final choice
and he moves into the pixel town and
everyone's happy and then Mary Moxon and
she does exactly the same and she will
partially based her choice on Bob's
color choice because now he is her
neighbor and she knows she can trust him
since he bought exactly same menu and so
this process is repeated until the whole
town is full and through this repeated
local behavior the resulting generated
image emerges to be perceptually similar
to this example image and I say emerge
because individual pixels and they were
actually aware of the full picture
they're part of and have no knowledge of
the example image as a whole but just
the disjoint collection of pattern rules
and this technique was first proposed in
1981 by Garber
but discarded due to computational
tractability at the time and then
proposed again independently eighteen
years later by a person known in 99 and
became an origin of a whole subfield of
texture synthesis called nonparametric
detection synthesis and it was also my
first implementation in the texture
synthesis journey however the proposed
method was not perfect first of all it
was very slow for an example image of
just one hundred five hundred it is ten
thousand pattern examples we have to
have to be checked by every pixel we
synthesize so if we're generating an
image of one hundred by hundred with a
pattern of let's say twelve neighbors
there is 1.2 billion queries in total
secondly if a pixel doesn't have a good
matching pattern to follow it is still
forced to make a decision what color
should be
no matter how a bad decision turns out
but that in turn means that the
following pixels will also be more
likely to make a poor decision as they
will be influenced by the previous
decisions thus it creates a chain
reaction of poorly chosen pixels
resulting in garbage growing and as it
is seen in the example on the right we
have places where details are completely
lost and become smudged uncertain mass
so one of the solutions to the first
problem the problem of slowness was
three search for closes matching pattern
and it was first proposed in fast techno
synthesis using tree structure to vector
quantization however the technique has a
requirement for all the search queries
to adhere to the same format as we could
no longer have an arbitrary pattern of
neighbors it had to be fixed
across all pixels so a scanline order
became a natural solution another
contribution from this paper which was
used before in texture synthesis but now
with nonparametric flavor was
multi-resolution synthesis where you
decompose example in image into an image
pyramid which is the same image but at
multiple resolution scales and we
generate starting from the lowest
resolution all the way to the highest
and the intuition behind this is that by
having some information from the
previous level but sort of gives you a
general idea of a bigger picture around
you in the current resolution level and
quite a curious property of this
algorithm is that you start generating
from noise which is refined to look more
and more plausible from multiple
resolution levels as more and more
details are being synthesized or if you
want to add AI vibe to this you can say
that the details are being imagined from
the noise by the algorithm but now it's
just time for investigate search and
here is just a small example that no
matter what image we start with as our
lowest level of parameter actually this
one's example we will end up with
something that resembles the original
example image because those has the only
patterns that are available for the
algorithm to operate on and I guess one
can treat this as a sort of funky style
transfer always image pyramids
coming back to the garbage growing
problem a series of patch based
techniques were proposed as it was
noticed that very few pixels actually
had multiple choices of what they can be
and often are completely determined but
what has been generated around them
thus the logic is why waste complete
power on synthesizing individual pixels
when were inevitably copying bigger
patches so let's just shortcut to
copying bigger patches and then hide the
seams between those so kind of like a
mosaic or a jigsaw puzzle and then there
was another very interesting technique
proposed in synthesizing natural
textures that touched on both the speed
of the search as well as budget based
synthesis so what we do is ask each of
our neighbors where did they come from
in the original example image and
neighbors from the generated image and
based on that we determine what like
what our color can be so you can think
of it as every neighbor makes a
suggestion of what next pixel color
should be and then we also add a couple
of random candidates from the example
just in case all of our neighbors had
terrible ideas and the result is not
just massively sped up search since we
greatly reduced the number of candidates
that's the size of our menu but also
she's in many cases we are going along
with neighbors suggestions we are
effectively copying patches but in a
very irregular shape avoiding obvious
seams between pieces like here but since
there are only dozen of patterns to pick
from we are no longer dependent on a
tree structure search to do it fast thus
we do not really care for a scanline
order anymore in fact the resolution
order can be completely arbitrary and in
his dissertation image detection tools
Paul Harrison proposed let's just do it
at random and it is very curious because
it is implicitly multiscale so why is
that so let's imagine that this is an
image being generated and pink purple
cells are resolved pixels and orange is
a pixel being resolved now and let's say
we are checking just for three closest
resolved neighbors as our neighborhood
pattern so in the case of iteration 20
since not so many pixels have been
raised
yet we have a big search radius meaning
we capture more gullible further away
information but it is also rather sparse
opposed to iteration 200 where our three
nearest neighbor are much closer to us
resulting in a tighter search radius
where we only capture immediate but it
is also more frequent information and as
more my pixels get resolved our search
radius shrinks so kind of naturally we
go from big sparse search to a smaller
local one and the second idea introduced
with image detection tools was ok let's
say our initial color guess was far from
ideal we didn't know much at the time
and we based our color on very few
faraway pixels and now we are not
fitting in with a new color pixels that
have been generated around us and that
is fine because we can choose again and
again and again
as many time as what you as as many
times as you perform what is called
backtracking so here's a comparison of
generating this gradient image on the
right with and without backtracking and
as you can see without backtracking we
have to stick with our initial choices
no but no matter how bad they are and
our uncertainty which is basically the
error of the chosen pixels it stays
unchanged opposed to the backtracking
version where we are able to reduce the
error by choosing again based on the new
information around us and this is an
example of a generated image and we can
get a couple of nice visualizations such
as places of uncertainty which are
usually located where the copied patch
is made in this copied patches
visualization and here's the same color
it means that the whole patch the same
color has be just straight corporate
from the example and that also gives a
nice intuition into what is happening
which you can think of as mixing the
image up and gluing the patches together
as best as possible and this is how the
resolution process looks like an action
and at this point it was already my
fourth Python prototype of texture
synthesis
and it was a version they decided to
take further as both its implicit
multiscale neighbor search as well as
ability to correct mistakes looked quite
promising and too much the whole bag and
myself had a couple of contributions
that we added along the way first of all
we noticed that because of the algorithm
stochastic nature during early stages of
resolution the sparse neighbor
information can be misleading so let's
say that this is image we have as
example and we just generated this three
brown pixels so far now if you want to
resolve this pixel in the red cell we
have quite a bit of ambiguity whether it
is a house so it will be brown or it's a
three green and if we look at the
kinetic patterns are exactly the same
for both three in the house from this
kernels so what do we in this case and
what'll happen it will just have a patch
of the house and the tree trying to
fight with each other who actually has
the right to be in the image resulting
in a very obvious seam as will just try
to blend between them and our
observation was that in the beginning
you don't really care for specific pixel
colors you care more about the global
distribution of stuff in the image
making sense and that is why we start
with generating a blurry version of the
image where a lot of pixel values are
averaged out with their neighbors that's
sort of encoding information about the
surroundings and then progressively
switch to sharper version of the image
as we have more and more result pixels
in this way for example in this house
and three case we avoids ambiguity as we
can clearly see that three is more
brownish green and houses more brownish
red and here is an example of the
resolution stages of the algorithm and
we can also control how many of those
levels we want to go through and how
much percent of total image is resolved
at each stage and when comparing to
vanilla version we noticed much better
remixing as the vanilla version hangs on
to details are already at the early
stages which results in trying to teach
multiple islands together only the later
stages and it creates more obvious seams
whereas the most resolution forces us to
consider more global distribution from
early on and we also got much more
interesting stalin's results as it
preserves more original style features
such as this kind of flowers
but after star transfer testing we
notice that the increased neighbor count
yielded worse results in staying within
the range of 20 and we hypothesize that
it might be due to all neighbors no
matter how close or far they are they
were weighted equally so that means that
once you have a lot of neighbors there
are more further further away once than
the close ones and then skews the
generation to satisfy the majority which
are the farthest ones thus sacrificing
the immediate neighbors in favor of
dominant distant ones but the solution
was rather simple actually even used in
the original nonparametric texture
synthesis paper over weighing each
neighbor based on just how far away it
is from the pixel we're solving and as
you can see especially with style
transfer we drastically reduce the
garbage growing in this cases we have a
lot of the same color because it wasn't
sure what to do now we have a much
better pattern so last but not least
here is a people comparing house and
they prefer nonparametric
implementations I did n times it takes
for various image sizes I tried to keep
the settings as similar as possible to
have a fair comparison and the settings
between the last two are is the same and
being evangelized by my colleagues
re-implemented the random order
algorithm in rust programming language
which out of the box actually was about
20 times faster than Python and then
together with Tom just over the weekend
we did a bunch of micro optimizations
such as using our star tree for nearest
neighbor search when constructing the
neighborhood pattern and Thomas added
CPU multi-threading and because the
algorithm is stochastic and pixel
resolution does not strictly depend on
what has been synthesized immediately
before and even if it does a lot of
errors will be corrected in the
backtracking
it was pretty straightforward to multi
thread so overall it was a pretty
massive speed up from my first
implementation and now is our latest
version we get 500 by 500 - now 1/2
seconds and one thousand five one
thousand in under ten and that is if
you're generating the whole image from
scratch because you can also just
generate a part of an image and it is
going to be faster because it mostly
depends just on the number of pixels
that you want to resolve
and just to summarize this section of
the presentation I would like to take a
moment tomorrow at how you're really
always building on the shoulder of
giants and the work that has been done
before inspires and enables to do
something new and this is just a small
humble addition there's a chain of
really awesome ideas but now let's talk
about how texture synthesis can be used
and like to think of use cases as
artifacts of an archaeological
expedition where we have the ultimate
goal but we also discover a bunch of
interesting stuff along the way that we
can use already today so first and most
obvious we can generate new similar
looking images from an example image and
we even have a sue deterministic seed
and it is pseudo because of
multi-threading as we cannot guarantee
which thread picks up which pixel but
generally you almost don't see the
difference between the outcomes so I
guess practice you can probably use this
feature as find ten differences puzzle
generator but super hard code mode we
can also guide the generation by
providing a mapping in a form of guide
maps which are this abstract kind of low
effort images either black and white or
RGB and you can map a certain part of
the image to be circle or any other
shape like in the example on the Left
where I took this photo fluid and I
asked it to go from this shape to this
shape and as you can see we also can get
different variations or you can do a
more involved semantic guidance like
here where semantically mark that green
is Ivy and blue is the wall and red is
window and then I just asked for a
different kind of shape of Ivy and just
two windows and generated that and it is
I think is really quite convenient and
interesting because you're manipulating
from a higher abstraction level than the
image content itself and this kind of
guidance can also be generated
automatically to produce style transfer
type of effect so what we are basically
doing is we generate guide maps as
luminance of your target and example
maps then we do some histogram matching
apply some Gaussian blur and use the
same process as in the previous slide
and if you're like me and Tom you can
sync
whole weekend and generating some spaces
because it's that addicting but apart
from that we were actually quite
impressed with the algorithms ability to
preserve style features and remap the
image to still look like a face and of
course you can also control how much
style versus content you would like so
you can go from one which means you want
to fully preserve the original content
or you can go or you can lower it which
in the context of the algorithm just
means how much it weighs the cost
between style and content when choosing
best candidates and this is controlled
by the Alpha parameter and it it is also
extremely adaptive which means the more
pixels get resolved the smaller gets
until we don't care for it at all
meaning we just put it to zero and that
is done to not penalize smaller detail
creation during the later stages but
moving on we can also do tiling textures
we can add a synthesized one from
scratch like in the example on the left
or we can edit the original known tiling
image and make it tile like on the
example on the right and the most
exciting feature is the variation of
tiling you get kind of like in this
example in the place of the seam we can
either just get some dark vegetation or
an actual flower or hit the generate
butter again and get something new we
can also fill in missing information and
again we get a bunch of variations
pretty much for free and even when a lot
of information is missing like in this
bark example it is still able to
possibly restore the image just from the
existing data which is not direct pixels
and is not limited to saturation from a
single image we can have multiple
examples which can be used to mix
multiple images together so the
visualization on the right kind of gives
you a hint from the map idea where each
color indicates from which image the
patches were taken but let me show you
more explicitly what came from where
says it's from there and this part came
from there and I like how just
make us so stir together and this part
came from here pretty exciting to see it
I was able to do that pretty nicely and
we can also start layering all of those
verbs we just went through so how about
molds example guy degeneration here I'm
generating 30 new Russian ethnic windows
from only five examples and
corresponding guide maps and then I
asked to basically transform those
images and mix them in such a way that I
base my target guide map and to help
generation little bit I also include
spatial information in the form of a
gradient in the red channel in the guide
Maps you can see the red goes from 1 to
0 and I also generate only hump of the
image and mirror it in the end but this
is was quite a curious neat workflow for
exploring variations out of very small
datasets and no training required and
why be limited only to 2d we can also do
3d if we can represent it as textured
data such as displacement maps then just
from a single Rock example we can
generate more using the same texture
synthesis code and in order to correlate
displacement data with scholar data we
set it up as a hierarchical generation
where we first generate displacement
guided by user guide maps and then we
generate color guided by Z displacement
Maps therefore the color is aware of the
shape of the rock so we naturally get
dirt in the creases grass in the flatter
areas and so on and those dependencies
are automatically captured for us and
imagine if you get a big a library of
rock examples and then we could remix
may be multiple rocks together our
artists have used texture synthesis for
some of their terrain workflows where
they start with large-scale terrain
laser scan data but it comes with a lot
of undesired elements such as shadows
roads and trees and tension synthesis
together with photoshop's content-aware
fill can be used to clean that up and
kondal feel is good it's on its own like
average color filament but as pontus
room and our environment artist points
out texture synthesis can provide high
quality details that you can't generate
otherwise and they fit together with the
image seamlessly
and then Ponder's had a really cool idea
one we can use the difference between
before and after to extract actual
placement masks for in-game assets such
as trees and bushes so here's just an
example of before and after and this is
by the way 16 K image so it took a while
ranging between 10 to 15 minutes to
generate so it's not really real time
workflow but still vastly faster than
doing manually and we can have a nice
coffee break while it does the work for
us and here's just a small snippet of
the internal show-and-tell what you're
looking at is our first environment test
the purpose of this test was to see how
far we could push the size and scale of
our worlds with a small team using smart
techniques and tools this is a 256
square kilometer train but another 3,000
square kilometer backdrop to add to the
sense of scale to build it we used laser
scanned terrain data and satellite
imagery with our own in-house tech we
filter out unwanted data from the ground
surface satellite image like bushes and
trees we then used our internal texture
synthesis tool to procedurally generate
replacement data and add a real 3d
assets to populate the world combined
with a procedurally generated snow and
weather system
the result is an environment that feels
lifelike and dynamic filled with
naturally placed rocks grass bushes
roots and just a note
Pontus asked me to point upon this asked
me to point out he said texture
synthesis is used for generating
placements what he actually meant is
generating placement masks because of
the we just use it as an image of
difference before and after and by the
way if you you want to see more of the
crazy awesome work our artists are doing
to check out the medium blog posts where
we showcase our first environment test
and also talk about our photogrammetry
workflows and speaking of photogrammetry
another application of texture synthesis
is filling in missing information from
photogrammetry where often we are
missing a chunk of mesh due to its
inaccessibility during the scanning
process so let me show our very first
version 0.001 prototype automatically
detecting
that happens and filling in both mesh
and texture data so we start by
receiving a scanned asset with in this
case three maps the number can be
arbitrary and those are kind of made-up
Maps here and a missing chunk on the
bottom we use Houdini to fill as a mesh
hole and mark it with white to indicate
this part of the mesh needs texture
synthesis and the user can additionally
paint other areas they would like to
regenerate maybe there is a part of the
photogrammetry map for the demands that
they didn't like like some kind of a
noise or dirt and let's say that this is
a power that they would like to remove
or just have a different variation so in
this case the user mark two parts one on
top and one on the side so this is a
user mark areas and this one is was
marked automatically because the mesh
was missing there and here's how the
process looks like in action for each
marks every generation Island we create
its own in painted map that is unwrapped
in a continuous way and this is just to
ensure that there is no seams between
original and generated textures and to
make sure that all provides maps match
we also record a history of what texture
synthesis deed and apply the same
transformation to all of the maps so in
this look example we get three maps and
they match perfectly between each other
so if one of them was a roughness for
example it would still go naturally with
the color information and now you can
see the final high poly mesh with a
column of applied and the synthesized
parts fit seamlessly with the original
texture and this house the original
color looked like before texture
synthesis was applied and then we can
just use this high poly mesh and proceed
to baking it to low poly just the way we
usually do so now let's talk about some
of the limitations of this approach so
first of all it's pretty bad with
complex semantics that go beyond picks a
color unless you use a semantic guide
map like in the video generation example
but otherwise it has no understanding of
what is generating so you might end up
with pretty illogical seams but the
algorithm would insist they totally make
sense from purely local neighborhood
perspective
second limitation is that it's not that
great for textures featuring a very
precise ordered pattern
because then it has troubles stitching
them together due to its a stochastic
resolution nature increasing neighbor
count helps but even then you will most
likely end up with discontinuities in
your outcome it also cannot infer new
information that only operates and was
already there in the example image and
in this example as you can see it had
troubles blending that blue corner which
also manifested itself in the
uncertainty map as most red is
concentrated there and if we investigate
dialysis just highlighting what I have
mentioned but if we investigate copied
patches map we can see how much real
mixing went into the left side of the
image so it can become pretty granular
which intuitively we can think of it
really had to come up with something new
since it doesn't have a precise answer
in the example and then doesn't
necessarily mean it book fail coming up
with something plausible and yes it's
like you see the bigger patches here
because it had examples but as soon as
something it hasn't seen before it had
to continue this part it had to come up
with very very granular remix in but a
bit more illustrative example of this
limitation is asking to continue how
circle on a gradient background but it
completely fails because first of all it
doesn't have examples of how curvature
looks like on the other side of the
circle plus it doesn't separate circle
from a background for the algorithm
those are inseparable concepts that
exist only together because that's how
it's saw it in the example image and it
is why in this zoomed in example image
we get dark blue because it's sample
probably is those like when I started
resolving it sampled it from somewhere
here and now it had like them together
so it has no understanding and you can
also see how it manifests is uncertain
seen this very noisy border and last
this algorithm is designed for small
datasets if you have a library of
thousand images the likelihood that
we'll use better sample from a
particular image becomes more unlikely
the more images we add in most cases the
algorithm will just go along with
neighbor suggestions as completely
eliminating using too many example
images however it doesn't mean it will
not benefit from having more examples it
just means that the likelihood operator
mixing a lot of images together is very
small so you're more likely to end up
with something like I don't know three
or five images used out of the total
thousand you might provide in your
library so to summarize we have talked
about the vision of accessible creation
and that one way to approach this is
with example based synthesis that allows
anyone to describe their own generative
possibility spaces we talked about how
texture synthesis works where every
pixel is programmed by our examples and
by interacting with each other pixels
emerge to look similar because I get it
through this example image and we went
through some use cases and all of those
verbs such as guided multi example
single example in painting tiling and
how combination of those verbs can be
used for terrain workflows geometry
generation style transfer and
photogrammetry cleanup and then we
touched on the limitations of our
texture synthesis approach to highlight
that it is not the Silver Bullet for
image generation and also the future I
firmly believe that the next step for
creative tools is ability to generate
programmer presentations from our
creative intent sort of frameworks or
method tools that can be filled without
infer the rules and as for our own
research our next step with example
based is moving towards 3d we already
started looking into that and looking
into like things like inverse procedural
modeling where procedural rules are
created from examples and even have our
first baby results but that's maybe a
talk for the next year and if you're
interested in digging deeper into
detection synthesis and the
nonparametric texture synthesis here is
a list of references used in this
presentation and I think we probably
will upload it online otherwise quickly
take a picture and before we wrap up I
would like to give a shout out to the
whole embark team this image is not very
representative anymore since we welcome
so many new faces in the first month but
I just want to say that it is an
absolute pleasure to work with such
talented people on the topics I deeply
care for
and that would be it thank you very much
for listening and if it's at that time I
have a question
[Applause]
questions guess so
okay I guess I can just repeat the
question so it is some people who will
watch it on videos I can hear it but we
can probably do the QA if anyone has a
question just raise your hand yes others
I'd like to know how easy is to move
from your approach to to the synthesis
to the 3d
how much of your previous work are you
able to to use or do you need much more
are in the effort this is a really good
question so there are two ways we can go
about 3d so because 2d in images you can
strain to like a very greed like
representation you can go along with it
and just say okay the 3d is just going
to be an additional dimension it's gonna
be 3d but we still do voxels this is one
way to approach it
another very interesting way is to say
okay let's assume that it is not grid
like suddenly you have not problems but
more challenges because I need to deal
with something let's say is non regular
and there are actually very interesting
research into that which were called
example based placements where they are
not assuming that your placements are on
a grid but instead they create kind of a
connectivity mesh like a graph and they
try to find and they give me very
similar texture synthesis they try to
find similar looking rules you have used
and grow up from there is your question
and one last question is since we're
talking about procedural generation and
real-time generation obviously there's
no time for machine learning but have
you considered doing some sort of
heuristics approach or more like a
dynamic scripting based on results can
you elaborate what they look like
you'd get based on the results that you
have you'd have some sort of either
automatic or user based pass where you'd
filter okay these are way better I mean
isn't something between the typical ml
and more dynamic stuff
oh sorry and where you'd have your
system rewriting parts of the yes if I
think I know what you mean so correct me
if I'm will go in the wrong direction
but one of the interesting things I
think that comes from this kind of
approach is that you have a feedback
loop with a user so let's say that I
have generated my image but there is a
part I don't like and don't want ever to
see it again
all I have to do is mark it as don't use
those rules and the interesting part is
that to create manually all of those
rules that is just in science a lot of
like there's 64,000 rules even for a
small image but we can curate that so we
can say oh my image has been generated I
really like it but this part I can mark
it oh can I do something else for
example if let's say we're generating a
field of strawberries with houses and
you like this part but you don't like
this part you can mark it for the
generation while keeping the rest intact
so I think that's why it's so
interesting to have systems that are
self-organizing because every single
pixel has to know about is what are the
rules I'm following and who are my
neighbors and that is it yes hey um I
was thinking about the example you
showed with the the yellow circle on the
blue one
yeah and I'm wondering if do you guys
ever consider different orientations of
each one of the blocks and even flipped
you imagine that it could under the back
side of it would be like with you know
spun versions of those yes you can
totally in an example when you provide
your example image you just provide
different versions of it so for example
you can provide them indeed flipped you
can provide the mirror to rotate it or
even in different scales so it will
actually use parts of the let's say we
have a flower but we provide a small
flower medium flower a big flower then
it would be able to use all of them but
you provide them at the cost of growing
the amount of example example rules you
have and this is I think where it comes
from the it cannot infer or
generalize this information it has to be
explicit in those neighborhood rules I
think this question there as well yes
so the question is how we used texture
synthesis to texture a match like from
scratch there's no record yeah if you
just use some imaginary rules to make
something very abstract for example can
you texture that by using reference
textures that comes from photogrammetry
like if for example you scan ten books
take their textures and then you make
something very alien and then take
straight with that yes I think it's
actually one of the very interesting
applications we haven't tapped into that
basically you can have smart materials
and if you provide information in terms
of guide maps of let's say hey when you
curvature is this and your normal map
looks like this and something else then
this is your color and you can use it
when you sculpt the new mesh because
then you're basically changing all of
those parameters and it will find those
example patterns from the reference
library you provided so indeed you
basically can provide hey I have five
rocks and they look like this I'm going
to make something new now but the
texture yes it should look like
something like of those five rocks yes
so that would be I think really awesome
but we haven't tested ourselves okay
thank you
anyone else either so question there hey
great talk so you talked a bit about how
this is better than photo shops
content-aware fill but have you compared
it to other things like generative
adverse cellar adversarial networks and
maybe to maximum GU means wavefunction
collapse mm-hmm
so just a small correction I didn't say
that was better than condor fulfil I was
saying as we are also using it together
but to your question of comparing it to
ganz
or wavefunction collapse so comparing it
with ganz I think one of the why we
start doing this research is because we
were interesting and okay can we do
something from very small data sets
something that would not require
training because if we are interested in
pretty interactive experiences and let's
say someone wants to make a vampire
castle how much data do we have on that
or a mermaid Gil oh I don't know evil
would come up as probably crazy stuff so
they should be able to it should be very
intuitive the way they create those
rules and they should be able to create
them just from making something so this
was one of those with very famishing
collapse I have looked at it and its
really awesome I think one of it may be
better for some publications but when
we're generating something very big I'm
very like large image or even a bigger
volume sometimes it's better because
face wave function collapse the rules
are very hard constraint so it cannot
end up in a dead ends and we were
thinking can we avoid that even if the
generation is not going to be perfect
because then the user probably well it
looks a bit weird I'll like can we get
to this like 90 or 80 percent oh sweet
nice and then user may probably
regenerate something but we didn't want
to just say that oh this is like a dead
end so it answers the question
anymore yes so it's everything it's all
this supposed to be offline calculations
since this based on tensorflow I guess
this is not based on tensor flow but or
now yes we are using it for offline but
if you're generating a very small image
then it is milliseconds it feels
generating something very small like 50
by 50 but as soon as you're going bigger
like I was saying if we have about 500
by 500 that is tuna 1/2 seconds but we
are not using tensor flow and it is also
not GPU accelerated at the moment so
maybe if it is it will be even faster
but we are now just using CPU
multi-threading so it's your own
structure on it or I cannot miss the
start so we are not we're not using
tensor flow we brought it from scratch
in rust from scratch we use a rest
libraries that's great but we roll the
whole framework from scratch in rust
very cool
thank you we have one minute left so we
can I guess have time for one very small
question if anyone willing to take again
I guess that's it thank you very much
[Applause]